<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Parallel Programming on Nico Holmberg</title>
    <link>https://nholmber.github.io/categories/parallel-programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Parallel Programming on Nico Holmberg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nholmber.github.io/categories/parallel-programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing I/O operations with MPI, Part 2: Performance tuning and Cray Burst Buffer</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/12/mpi-io-cube-pt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/12/mpi-io-cube-pt2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the benefits of using the message passing interface (MPI) to parse large data files in parallel over multiple processors. In today&amp;rsquo;s post, I will demonstrate how MPI I/O operations can be further accelerated by introducing the concept of hints. The second topic I will discuss is the emergence of solid-state drives in high-performance computing systems to resolve I/O bottlenecks. These topics will be illustrated by benchmark calculations using a parallel writer routine that I will implement to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/&#34;&gt;task described previously&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing I/O operations with MPI: A case study with volumetric data</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately, parsing volumetric data from large (&amp;gt; 300 MB) text files has been a computational bottleneck in my simulations. Because I expect to be processing hundreds of these files, I decided to parallelize the parser routine by leveraging the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Message_Passing_Interface&#34;&gt;message passing interface&lt;/a&gt; (MPI). I will describe my first experience with MPI I/O in this post by going through the synthesis process of the parallelized parser routine. I will also examine the performance of the parallel parser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>