<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Nico Holmberg</title>
    <link>https://nholmber.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Nico Holmberg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nholmber.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Update: September 2018</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/09/research-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/09/research-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The arrival of a new batch of freshmen is a sure sign of autumn and the start of a new academic semester. I am thrilled to announce that this semester should also be my last one as a Ph.D. candidate because I officially submitted my dissertation for preliminary examination last week. In this post, I will look back on summer 2018 and recap the research projects that I completed during that time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Google Colaboratory into Your Machine Learning Workflow</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/09/google-colab/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/09/google-colab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Are you using &lt;a href=&#34;https://jupyter.org&#34;&gt;Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a&gt; regularly in your machine learning or data science projects? Did you know that you can work on notebooks inside a free cloud-based environment with a GPU accelerator? In this post, I will introduce you to &lt;a href=&#34;https://colab.research.google.com&#34;&gt;Google Colaboratory&lt;/a&gt; and show you in a few simple steps how to integrate this platform into your daily workflow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Geographic Statistical Data with Google Maps</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/08/gmaps-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/08/gmaps-statistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This tutorial will teach you how to create a custom Google Maps based map for visualizing geographic statistical data. Such maps can be a useful tool when developing machine learning models. As a specific example case, we will create a map for visualizing the population density and median household income of postal code areas in Finland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matrix diagonalization in parallel computing: Benchmarking ELPA against ScaLAPACK</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/05/mpi-diagonalization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/05/mpi-diagonalization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Matrix diagonalization is a fundamental linear algebra operation with a wide range of applications in scientific and other fields of computing. At the same time, it is also one of the most expensive operations with a formal &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computational_complexity_of_mathematical_operations&#34;&gt;computational complexity&lt;/a&gt; of $\mathcal{O}(N^3)$, which can become a significant performance bottleneck as the size of the system grows. In this post, I will introduce the canonical algorithm for diagonalizing matrices in parallel computing to set the scene for today&amp;rsquo;s main topic: improving diagonalization performance. With the help of benchmark calculations, I will then demonstrate how a clever mathematical library choice can easily reduce the time needed to diagonalize a matrix by at least 50 %.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A recap of the CP2K-UK 2018 meeting</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/01/cp2k-uk-2018-recap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2018/01/cp2k-uk-2018-recap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2018 edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cp2k.org/events:2018_user_meeting:index&#34;&gt;CP2K UK user meeting&lt;/a&gt; was held two Fridays ago at the University of Lincoln, UK. I will be recaping my experiences of the event in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constrained DFT tutorial at the CP2K-UK 2018 meeting</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/12/cp2k-uk-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/12/cp2k-uk-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I will be giving an introductory how-to talk on constrained DFT at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyurl.com/CP2K-2018&#34;&gt;2018 CP2K UK User meeting&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Lincoln, UK, on Friday January 12 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing I/O operations with MPI, Part 2: Performance tuning and Cray Burst Buffer</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/12/mpi-io-cube-pt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/12/mpi-io-cube-pt2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the benefits of using the message passing interface (MPI) to parse large data files in parallel over multiple processors. In today&amp;rsquo;s post, I will demonstrate how MPI I/O operations can be further accelerated by introducing the concept of hints. The second topic I will discuss is the emergence of solid-state drives in high-performance computing systems to resolve I/O bottlenecks. These topics will be illustrated by benchmark calculations using a parallel writer routine that I will implement to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/&#34;&gt;task described previously&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallelizing I/O operations with MPI: A case study with volumetric data</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/05/mpi-io-cube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately, parsing volumetric data from large (&amp;gt; 300 MB) text files has been a computational bottleneck in my simulations. Because I expect to be processing hundreds of these files, I decided to parallelize the parser routine by leveraging the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Message_Passing_Interface&#34;&gt;message passing interface&lt;/a&gt; (MPI). I will describe my first experience with MPI I/O in this post by going through the synthesis process of the parallelized parser routine. I will also examine the performance of the parallel parser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building CP2K on a Cray XC40</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/04/cp2k-build-cray-xc40/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/04/cp2k-build-cray-xc40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Compiling a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cp2k.org/&#34;&gt;CP2K&lt;/a&gt; binary &amp;ndash; the massively parallel, open-source quantum chemistry and solid state physics program written in Fortran 2003 &amp;ndash; can be a daunting task if you&amp;rsquo;ve never built a large project using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Make_(software)&#34;&gt;maketools&lt;/a&gt;. This post aims to demystify the build process by showcasing a full CP2K build on a Cray XC40 supercomputer (codename &lt;a href=&#34;https://research.csc.fi/sisu-supercomputer&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sisu&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) including dependencies.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to my website!</title>
      <link>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/02/welcome/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nholmber.github.io/2017/02/welcome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Greetings and welcome! You have stumbled upon the personal website and blog of Nico Holmberg, a 26 year old Finn pursuing a doctoral degree in Computational Quantum Chemistry. Feel free to check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../../profile&#34;&gt;profile&lt;/a&gt; for more information about me, my professional projects and other interests!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>